Guide to the Joseph Halle Schaffner Collection in the History of Science 1642-1961
University of Chicago Library
- Series III: Albert Einstein Correspondence and Photographs
  - Albert Einstein, AE. ADS, 1 p., 1 leaf. Document deals with dangers of atomic weapons and need for international peace (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Albert Einstein, AE, Princeton, to Joseph H. Schaffner, New York, 17 October 1946. TLS, 1 p., 1 leaf A letter of thanks from Einstein for Schaffner’s gift of a book (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Albert Einstein, A framed photograph of Einstein by Yousof Karsh. Given by Einstein to Schaffner. The following inscription is written on the mat below the photograph; "To Mr. Joseph Schaffner with kind regards A. Einstein, 50." (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Albert Einstein Photos framed together, AE, Princeton, to Bertold Neuer, New York, 26 October 1934. TLS, 1 p. Einstein thanks Neuer for a piano Photograph clipped from a magazine showing AE playing the violin (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Sir Isaac Newton, 1642-1727
  - Of an universall language (rough draft plus more finished draft) and other writings (genealogical notes; Latin phrases and English equivalents in a different hand). N.d., Autograph Ms (in a small notebook) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - For making portable furnaces, including a rough diagram. N.d. Autograph Ms. Four pages on two leaves, folded (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript on pyrotechny, illustrated with diagrams. N.d. Autograph Ms. Two pages on one folio leaf, folded (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript on certain chemical operations, "A Londoner acquainted with Mr. Boyle and Dr. Dickinson, affirmed that...ye oyle or spirit might be taken as sold in shops...," with the draft of a short letter mentioning Pepys on the reverse side. N.d. Autograph Ms. Two pages on one leaf (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Description of an instrument for determining the angular distance of the moon from any fixed star with chronological/theological notes on the reverse side. N.d. Autograph Ms. Two pages on one leaf (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Brief passage in Latin on the invention of the calculus (Begins; "Non quisnam hanc vel illam methodum invenerit...) on scrap of paper 2.5 inches by 7.5 inches. N.d. Autograph Ms. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pepys, Samuel to Sir Isaac Newton, 21 December 1693. ALS, two pages on one leaf (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Conduitt, John. "Memorandums relating to Sr. Isaac Newton given me by Mr. Abraham De Moivre in Novr. 1727." Autograph Ms. Five pages on two leaves (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bonval, B. de, La Haye, to Sir Isaac Newton, 22 August, [1697?]. ALS, 1 p., 1 leaf, Sir Isaac Newton, manuscripts, See Series VII: Oversize (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Series V: Miscellaneous Scientific Manuscripts
  - John Carver. Notes on mathematical and geometrical problems from Sir Isaac Newton’s Principia and other works. September 7-February 1, 1820 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - [Siussi, Johannes Fracisco]. Translation notes and diagram from M. D’Alembert, Traite de l’equilibre, Paris; David, 1744 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Alessandro Giuseppe Antonio Anastasio Volta, Conte, 1745-1827, Como, to Padre G. B. Beccaria. A.L.S., 1 p. From Alessandro Volta, Lettere...Sull’Aria Infiammabile Nativa Della Paludi... Milano; Giuseppe Marelli, 1777 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series VI: Schaffner Collection Records
  - Records pertaining to the history of the Schaffner Collection. The Curie manuscripts, See also Series VII: Oversize (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Records pertaining to the history of the Schaffner Collection. The Darwin manuscripts, See also Series VII: Oversize (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Records pertaining to the history of the Schaffner Collection. The Einstein manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Records pertaining to the history of the Schaffner Collection. The Newton manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Huntington Library exhibition of Newton manuscripts, January-May, 1943, See also Series VII: Oversize (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ralph Elliot, Correspondence with Schaffner regarding Newton’s "Of an universall language.", See also Series VII: Oversize (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Henry P. McComber, Correspondence with Schaffner regarding the Babson Institute Newton Collection and the Schaffner Newton Collection, 1954-61 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sir Lawrence Bragg, the Royal Society of London, H. M. Adams, Librarian of Trinity College, Cambridge, England, and others, correspondence regarding Schaffner and other Newton manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series VII: Oversize
  - Sir Isaac Newton, manuscripts, Dictionary of Latin phrases and An account of the charges of the mint in coyning and paying into the receipt of his majestie’s exchequer the new monies of the sixth general remain. In custom-made box of half red morocco An account of the charges of the mint in coyning and paying into the receipt of his majestie’s exchequer the new monies of the sixth general remain. 1 April 1696. Autograph Ms. 1 p., 1 leaf, folded. Signed by Newton and others A Latin phrase book with the first entry under the English heading "Abate" and the last under the heading "Conduct." N.d. Autograph Ms. 5 p., 3 leaves (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Records pertaining to the history of the Schaffner Collection. The Curie manuscripts (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Records pertaining to the history of the Schaffner Collection. The Darwin manuscripts (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Huntington Library exhibition of Newton manuscripts, January-May, 1943, See also Series VII: Oversize (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Ralph Elliot, Correspondence with Schaffner regarding Newton’s "Of an universall language.", See also Series VII: Oversize (Box 6, Folder 5)